{
  "chapter_metadata": {
    "chapter_id": "5.English.25",
    "standard": "5",
    "subject": "Environmental Studies",
    "medium": "English",
    "chapter_name": "Our Responsibility"
  },
  "questions": [
    {
      "question_id": 1,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Fun activity",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Duty to do the right thing",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Game",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Reward",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Duty to do the right thing"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 2,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Who has responsibilities?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Only adults",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Only children",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "All citizens",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Teachers only",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "All citizens"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 3,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why are responsibilities important?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "They waste time",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "They keep society orderly",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "They cause problems",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "They are optional",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "They keep society orderly"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 4,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is our responsibility towards environment?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Pollute it",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Protect it",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignore it",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Use more resources",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Protect it"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 5,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is pollution?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Clean air",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Harm to environment",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Rain",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Wind",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Harm to environment"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 6,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What causes pollution?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Plants",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Human activities",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Animals",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Rain",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Human activities"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 7,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which is biodegradable waste?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Plastic",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Glass",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Vegetable peels",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Metal",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Vegetable peels"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 8,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which is non-biodegradable waste?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Leaves",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Paper",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Plastic",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Food waste",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Plastic"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 9,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is recycling?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Throwing waste",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Reusing waste materials",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Burning waste",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Burying waste",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Reusing waste materials"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 10,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What are the 3Rs?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Read, Write, Learn",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Reduce, Reuse, Recycle",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Run, Rest, Relax",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Repair, Remove, Replace",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Reduce, Reuse, Recycle"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 11,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should we save water?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "It is unlimited",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "It is limited",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "It is dirty",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "It is costly",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "It is limited"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 12,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is water conservation?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Wasting water",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Saving water",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Polluting water",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Storing water",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Saving water"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 13,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should electricity be saved?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "For fun",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "To conserve resources",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "To increase bills",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "To use more power",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "To conserve resources"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 14,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which is a renewable resource?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Coal",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Petrol",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Solar energy",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Diesel",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Solar energy"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 15,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which is a non-renewable resource?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Wind",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Solar",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Coal",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Water",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Coal"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 16,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why are trees important?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "They cause pollution",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "They give oxygen",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "They reduce rain",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "They waste space",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "They give oxygen"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 17,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is deforestation?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Planting trees",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Cutting down trees",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Watering plants",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Growing crops",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Cutting down trees"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 18,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is afforestation?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Cutting trees",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Planting new trees",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Burning forests",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Using wood",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Planting new trees"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 19,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is wildlife?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Pets",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Animals in forests",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Farm animals",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Zoo animals",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Animals in forests"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 20,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should wildlife be protected?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "For fun",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "To maintain balance",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "To sell animals",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "To reduce forests",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "To maintain balance"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 21,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is cleanliness?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Making noise",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Keeping surroundings clean",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Throwing waste",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Using plastic",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Keeping surroundings clean"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 22,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should we keep our surroundings clean?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "To look dirty",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "To stay healthy",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "To pollute",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "To waste time",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "To stay healthy"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 23,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is civic sense?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Bad behavior",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Good behavior in public",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Private work",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Personal rule",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Good behavior in public"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 24,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should public property be protected?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "It belongs to one person",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "It belongs to all",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "It is useless",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "It is private",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "It belongs to all"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 25,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Which is public property?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "House",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Road",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Shop",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Farm",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Road"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 26,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is discipline?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Breaking rules",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Following rules",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignoring rules",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Making rules",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Following rules"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 27,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why is discipline important?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "It creates problems",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "It builds character",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "It wastes time",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "It causes fear",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "It builds character"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 28,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is honesty?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Lying",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Speaking truth",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Cheating",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Hiding facts",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Speaking truth"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 29,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why is honesty important?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "It builds trust",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "It causes trouble",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "It wastes time",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "It hides truth",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "It builds trust"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 30,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is cooperation?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Fighting",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Working together",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignoring others",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Competing",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Working together"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 31,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why is cooperation important?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "For success",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "For failure",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "For fights",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "For isolation",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "For success"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 32,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is sharing?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Keeping everything",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Giving part to others",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Taking from others",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Hiding things",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Giving part to others"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 33,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should we share?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "It builds kindness",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "It causes loss",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "It wastes resources",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "It creates fights",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "It builds kindness"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 34,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards elders?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Ignore them",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Respect and care",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Argue",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Avoid them",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Respect and care"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 35,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards teachers?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Ignore them",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Respect and obey",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Argue",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Disobey",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Respect and obey"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 36,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is road safety responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Breaking rules",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Following traffic rules",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Speeding",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Ignoring signals",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Following traffic rules"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 37,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should traffic rules be followed?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "To prevent accidents",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "To waste time",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "To break laws",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "To run fast",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "To prevent accidents"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 38,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is digital responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Misusing internet",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Using technology wisely",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Spreading rumors",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Hacking",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Using technology wisely"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 39,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is Swachh Bharat Abhiyan?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Education scheme",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Clean India mission",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Health scheme",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Sports event",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Clean India mission"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 40,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Who started Swachh Bharat Abhiyan?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Students",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Government of India",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Teachers",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Doctors",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Government of India"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 41,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is national duty?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Personal work",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Duty towards country",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Family duty",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "School work",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Duty towards country"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 42,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is good citizenship?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Breaking rules",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Following duties sincerely",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignoring laws",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Only voting",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Following duties sincerely"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 43,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What happens if responsibilities are ignored?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Peace increases",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Problems increase",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Society improves",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Nothing happens",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Problems increase"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 44,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is environmental responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Polluting environment",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Protect environment",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignoring nature",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Using more plastic",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Protect environment"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 45,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should children learn responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "To become good citizens",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "To avoid school",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "To waste time",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "To disobey",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "To become good citizens"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 46,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is moral responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Doing wrong",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Doing right things",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignoring values",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Cheating",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Doing right things"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 47,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is self-discipline?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Losing control",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Controlling oneself",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Ignoring rules",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Breaking habits",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Controlling oneself"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 48,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Who benefits if we act responsibly?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Only adults",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Everyone",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Only children",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Only government",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Everyone"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 49,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "What is our biggest responsibility?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "Earning money",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "Protect Earth",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "Using resources",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "Building houses",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "Protect Earth"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 50,
      "question_type": "MCQ",
      "question": "Why should we act responsibly every day?",
      "options": [
        {
          "option_id": 1,
          "text": "For fun",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 2,
          "text": "For better future",
          "is_correct": true
        },
        {
          "option_id": 3,
          "text": "For reward",
          "is_correct": false
        },
        {
          "option_id": 4,
          "text": "For punishment",
          "is_correct": false
        }
      ],
      "answer": "For better future"
    },
    {
      "question_id": 51,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility?",
      "answer": "Duty to do the right thing."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 52,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Who has responsibilities?",
      "answer": "All citizens."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 53,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why are responsibilities important?",
      "answer": "They keep society orderly."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 54,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is our responsibility towards family?",
      "answer": "To care and respect."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 55,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is our responsibility towards school?",
      "answer": "Follow rules and learn."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 56,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is our responsibility towards society?",
      "answer": "Help others."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 57,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is our responsibility towards nation?",
      "answer": "Be a good citizen."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 58,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is environment?",
      "answer": "Our natural surroundings."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 59,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we protect environment?",
      "answer": "For future safety."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 60,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is pollution?",
      "answer": "Harm to environment."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 61,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What causes pollution?",
      "answer": "Human activities."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 62,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is air pollution?",
      "answer": "Polluted air."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 63,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What causes air pollution?",
      "answer": "Smoke and vehicles."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 64,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is water pollution?",
      "answer": "Dirty water."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 65,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What causes water pollution?",
      "answer": "Waste dumping."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 66,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is land pollution?",
      "answer": "Dirty land."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 67,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is noise pollution?",
      "answer": "Excessive loud sound."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 68,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is pollution harmful?",
      "answer": "It affects health."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 69,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is cleanliness?",
      "answer": "Keeping surroundings clean."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 70,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we keep our surroundings clean?",
      "answer": "To stay healthy."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 71,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is waste?",
      "answer": "Things we throw away."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 72,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is waste management?",
      "answer": "Proper handling of waste."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 73,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is biodegradable waste?",
      "answer": "Waste that decomposes."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 74,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Give one biodegradable waste.",
      "answer": "Vegetable peels."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 75,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is non-biodegradable waste?",
      "answer": "Waste that does not decompose."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 76,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Give one non-biodegradable waste.",
      "answer": "Plastic."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 77,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is recycling?",
      "answer": "Reusing waste materials."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 78,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is recycling important?",
      "answer": "It saves resources."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 79,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is reuse?",
      "answer": "Using items again."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 80,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is reduce?",
      "answer": "Using less resources."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 81,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What are the 3Rs?",
      "answer": "Reduce, Reuse, Recycle."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 82,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we follow 3Rs?",
      "answer": "To protect environment."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 83,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is water conservation?",
      "answer": "Saving water."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 84,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should water be saved?",
      "answer": "It is limited."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 85,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is energy conservation?",
      "answer": "Saving energy."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 86,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should electricity be saved?",
      "answer": "To conserve resources."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 87,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is renewable resource?",
      "answer": "Resource that can be reused."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 88,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Give one renewable resource.",
      "answer": "Solar energy."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 89,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is non-renewable resource?",
      "answer": "Resource that gets exhausted."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 90,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Give one non-renewable resource.",
      "answer": "Coal."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 91,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is tree plantation?",
      "answer": "Planting trees."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 92,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why are trees important?",
      "answer": "They give oxygen."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 93,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What happens if trees are cut?",
      "answer": "Environment gets harmed."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 94,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is deforestation?",
      "answer": "Cutting down trees."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 95,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is deforestation harmful?",
      "answer": "It causes climate change."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 96,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is afforestation?",
      "answer": "Planting new trees."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 97,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is wildlife?",
      "answer": "Animals living in forests."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 98,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should wildlife be protected?",
      "answer": "To maintain balance."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 99,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is conservation?",
      "answer": "Protection of nature."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 100,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is natural balance?",
      "answer": "Balance in nature."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 101,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is climate change?",
      "answer": "Change in climate."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 102,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What causes climate change?",
      "answer": "Human actions."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 103,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is global warming?",
      "answer": "Rise in Earth’s temperature."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 104,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is global warming dangerous?",
      "answer": "It harms life."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 105,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards animals?",
      "answer": "Care and protection."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 106,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "How should we treat animals?",
      "answer": "With kindness."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 107,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards plants?",
      "answer": "Protect and grow them."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 108,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is public property?",
      "answer": "Property for public use."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 109,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we protect public property?",
      "answer": "It belongs to all."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 110,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Give one example of public property.",
      "answer": "Road."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 111,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is civic sense?",
      "answer": "Good behavior in public."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 112,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is civic sense important?",
      "answer": "For clean society."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 113,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is discipline?",
      "answer": "Following rules."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 114,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is discipline important?",
      "answer": "It builds character."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 115,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is honesty?",
      "answer": "Speaking truth."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 116,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is honesty important?",
      "answer": "It builds trust."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 117,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is respect?",
      "answer": "Showing value to others."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 118,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Whom should we respect?",
      "answer": "Everyone."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 119,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is cooperation?",
      "answer": "Working together."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 120,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why is cooperation important?",
      "answer": "For success."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 121,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is sharing?",
      "answer": "Giving part to others."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 122,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we share?",
      "answer": "It builds kindness."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 123,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards elders?",
      "answer": "Respect and care."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 124,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards children?",
      "answer": "Protect and guide."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 125,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards teachers?",
      "answer": "Respect and obey."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 126,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards neighbors?",
      "answer": "Help them."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 127,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility during disasters?",
      "answer": "Help and stay safe."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 128,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility as a student?",
      "answer": "Study sincerely."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 129,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is digital responsibility?",
      "answer": "Use technology wisely."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 130,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we use internet carefully?",
      "answer": "To stay safe."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 131,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is road safety responsibility?",
      "answer": "Follow traffic rules."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 132,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should traffic rules be followed?",
      "answer": "To prevent accidents."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 133,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is cleanliness drive?",
      "answer": "Campaign to clean areas."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 134,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is Swachh Bharat Abhiyan?",
      "answer": "Clean India mission."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 135,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Who started Swachh Bharat Abhiyan?",
      "answer": "Government of India."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 136,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards nation’s symbols?",
      "answer": "Respect them."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 137,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards Constitution?",
      "answer": "Follow its values."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 138,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is responsibility towards democracy?",
      "answer": "Participate responsibly."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 139,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is good citizenship?",
      "answer": "Following duties sincerely."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 140,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is national duty?",
      "answer": "Duty towards country."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 141,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is social responsibility?",
      "answer": "Responsibility towards society."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 142,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is environmental responsibility?",
      "answer": "Protect environment."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 143,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should children learn responsibility?",
      "answer": "To become good citizens."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 144,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What happens if responsibilities are ignored?",
      "answer": "Problems increase."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 145,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is moral responsibility?",
      "answer": "Doing right things."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 146,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is self-discipline?",
      "answer": "Controlling oneself."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 147,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is future responsibility?",
      "answer": "Protect resources for future."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 148,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Who will benefit if we act responsibly?",
      "answer": "Everyone."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 149,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "What is our biggest responsibility?",
      "answer": "Protect Earth."
    },
    {
      "question_id": 150,
      "question_type": "SHORT",
      "question": "Why should we act responsibly every day?",
      "answer": "For better future."
    }
  ]
}